<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-morton-ippm-2330-stdform-typep-00"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="2330">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Std-Formed and Type-P">Updates for IPPM's Active Metric
    Framework: Packets of Type-P and Standard-Formed Packets</title>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>

        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>

        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>

        <uri>http://home.comcast.net/~acmacm/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joachim Fabini" initials="J." surname="Fabini">
      <organization>Vienna University of Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gusshausstrasse 25/E389</street>

          <city>Vienna</city>

          <region/>

          <code>1040</code>

          <country>Austria</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+43 1 58801 38813</phone>

        <facsimile>+43 1 58801 38898</facsimile>

        <email>Joachim.Fabini@tuwien.ac.at</email>

        <uri>http://www.tc.tuwien.ac.at/about-us/staff/joachim-fabini/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Nalini Elkins" initials="N." surname="Elkins">
      <organization>Inside Products, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Carmel Valley </city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>93924</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>nalini.elkins@insidethestack.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael S. Ackermann" initials="M." surname="Ackermann">
      <organization>Blue Cross Blue Shield of Michigan</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>mackermann@bcbsmi.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vinayak Hegde" initials="V." surname="Hegde">
      <organization/>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>vinayakh@gmail.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="August" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo updates the IP Performance Metrics (IPPM) Framework RFC
      2330 with new considerations for measurement methodology and testing.
      The memo updates the definition of standard-formed packets in RFC 2330
      to include evaluation of IPv6 packets. It also augments examples of
      distinguishing aspects of packets, referred to as Type-P for test
      packets.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The IETF IP Performance Metrics (IPPM) working group first created a
      framework for metric development in <xref target="RFC2330"/>. This
      framework has stood the test of time and enabled development of many
      fundamental metrics. It has been updated in the area of metric
      composition <xref target="RFC5835"/>, and in several areas related to
      active stream measurement of modern networks with reactive properties
      <xref target="RFC7312"/>.</t>

      <t>The IPPM framework <xref target="RFC2330"/> recognized (in section
      13) that many aspects of IP packets can influence its processing during
      transfer across the network.</t>

      <t>In Section 15 of <xref target="RFC2330"/>, the notion of a
      "standard-formed" packet is defined. However, the definition was never
      updated to include IPv6, as the original authors planned.</t>

      <t>In particular, IPv6 Extension Headers and protocols which use IPv6
      header compression are growing in use. This memo seeks to provide the
      needed updates.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope">
      <t>The purpose of this memo is to expand the coverage of IPPM metrics to
      include IPv6, and to highlight additional aspects of test packets and
      make them part of the IPPM performance metric framework.</t>

      <t>The scope is to update key sections of <xref target="RFC2330"/>,
      adding considerations that will aid the development of new measurement
      methodologies intended for today's IP networks. Specifically, this memo
      expands the Type-P examples in section 13 of <xref target="RFC2330"/>
      and expands the definition (in section 15 of <xref target="RFC2330"/>)
      of a standard-formed packet to include IPv6 header aspects and other
      features.</t>

      <t>Other topics in <xref target="RFC2330"/> which might be updated or
      augmented are deferred to future work. This includes the topics of
      passive and various forms of hybrid active/passive measurements.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Packets of Type-P">
      <t>A fundamental property of many Internet metrics is that the value of
      the metric depends on the type of IP packet(s) used to make the
      measurement. Consider an IP-connectivity metric: one obtains different
      results depending on whether one is interested in connectivity for
      packets destined for well-known TCP ports or unreserved UDP ports, or
      those with invalid IPv4 checksums, or those with TTL or Hop Limit of 16,
      for example. In some circumstances these distinctions will be highly
      interesting (for example, if Diffserv <xref target="RFC2780"/>, ECN
      <xref target="RFC3168"/>, Router Alert, Hop-by-hop extensions <xref
      target="RFC7045"/>, or Flow Labels <xref target="RFC6437"/> are used, or
      in the presence of firewalls or RSVP reservations).</t>

      <t>Because of this distinction, we introduce the generic notion of a
      "packet of Type-P", where in some contexts P will be explicitly defined
      (i.e., exactly what type of packet we mean), partially defined (e.g.,
      "with a payload of B octets"), or left generic. Thus we may talk about
      generic IP-Type-P-connectivity or more specific
      IP-port-HTTP-connectivity. Some metrics and methodologies may be
      fruitfully defined using generic Type-P definitions which are then made
      specific when performing actual measurements.</t>

      <t>Whenever a metric's value depends on the type of the packets involved
      in the metric, the metric's name will include either a specific type or
      a phrase such as "Type-P". Thus we will not define an "IP-connectivity"
      metric but instead an "IP-Type-P-connectivity" metric and/or perhaps an
      "IP-port-HTTP-connectivity" metric. This naming convention serves as an
      important reminder that one must be conscious of the exact type of
      traffic being measured.</t>

      <t>If the information constituting Type-P at the Source is found to have
      changed at the Destination (or at a measurement point between the Source
      and Destination, as in <xref target="RFC5644"/>), then the modified
      values SHOULD be noted and reported with the results. Some modifications
      occur according to the conditions encountered in transit (such as
      congestion notification) or due to the requirements of segments of the
      Source to Destination path. For example, the packet length will change
      if IP header conversion to the alternate version/address family, or if
      optional extension headers are added or removed. Local policies in
      intermediate nodes based on examination of IPv6 extension headers may
      affect measurement repeatability, especially if the policy involves
      random assignment to resources in the node, for example. If intermediate
      nodes follow the recommendations of <xref target="RFC7045"/>,
      repeatability may be improved to some degree. </t>

      <t>A closely related note: it would be very useful to know if a given
      Internet component treats equally a class C of different types of
      packets. If so, then any one of those types of packets can be used for
      subsequent measurement of the component. This suggests we devise a
      metric or suite of metrics that attempt to determine C.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Standard-Formed Packets">
      <t>Unless otherwise stated, all metric definitions that concern IP
      packets include an implicit assumption that the packet is
      *standard-formed*. A packet is standard-formed if it meets all of the
      following criteria:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="+">It includes a valid IP header: see below for
          version-specific criteria.</t>

          <t hangText="+">It is not an IP fragment.</t>

          <t hangText="+">The source and destination addresses correspond to
          the intended Source and Destination, including Multicast Destination
          addresses.</t>

          <t hangText="+">If a transport header is present, it contains a
          valid checksum and other valid fields.</t>
        </list>Additionally, an IPv4 packet is standard-formed if it meets the
      following criteria:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The version field is 4; the header length is &gt;= 5; the
          checksum is correct.</t>

          <t>Its total length as given in the IPv4 header corresponds to the
          size of the IPv4 header plus the size of the payload.</t>

          <t>Either the packet possesses sufficient TTL to travel from the
          source to the destination if the TTL is decremented by one at each
          hop, or it possesses the maximum TTL of 255.</t>

          <t>It does not contain IP options unless explicitly noted.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Alternatively, an IPv6 packet is standard-formed if it meets the
      following criteria:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The version field is 6.</t>

          <t>Its total length corresponds to the size of the IPv6 header (40
          octets) plus the length of the payload (including extension headers)
          as given in the IPv6 header.</t>

          <t>Either the packet possesses sufficient Hop Count to travel from
          the Source to the Destination if the Hop Count is decremented by one
          at each hop, or it possesses the maximum Hop Count of 255.</t>

          <t>Either the packet does not contain IP extension headers, or it
          contains the correct number and type of headers as specified in the
          packet, and the headers appear in the expected order (Next
          Header).</t>

          <t>All parameters used in the header and extension headers will be
          found in the IANA Registry of Internet Protocol Version 6 (IPv6)
          Parameters, partly specified in <xref target="RFC7045"/>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Compressed IPv6 headers MUST be compliant with <xref
      target="RFC4494"/>, as updated by <xref target="RFC6282"/>, in order to
      be declared "standard-formed". </t>

      <t>The topic of IPv6 extension headers brings current controversies into
      focus. The following additional considerations apply when IPv6 extension
      headers are present:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Extension header inspection: Some intermediate nodes may inspect
          Extension Headers or the entire IPv6 packet while in transit. In
          exceptional cases, they may drop the packet or route via a
          sub-optimal path, and measurements may be unreliable or
          unrepeatable. The packet (if it arrives) may be standard-formed,
          with a corresponding Type-P. </t>

          <t>Extension header modification: In Hop-by-Hop headers, some TLV
          encoded options may be permitted to change at intermediate nodes
          while in transit. The resulting packet may be standard-formed, with
          a corresponding Type-P.</t>

          <t>Extension header insertion or deletion: It is possible that
          extension headers could be added to, or removed from the header
          chain. The resulting packet may be standard-formed, with a
          corresponding Type-P.</t>

          <t>A change in packet length (from the corresponding packet observed
          at the source) or header modification is a significant factor in
          Internet measurement, and requires a new Type-P to be reported.</t>
        </list>We further require that if a packet is described as having a
      "length of B octets", then 0 &lt;= B &lt;= 65535; and if B is the
      payload length in octets, then B &lt;= (65535-IP header size in octets,
      including any extension headers). The jumbograms defined in <xref
      target="RFC2675"/> are not covered by this length analysis. In practice,
      the path MTU will restrict the length of standard-formed packets that
      can successfully traverse the path.</t>

      <t>So, for example, one might imagine defining an IP connectivity metric
      as "IP-type-P-connectivity for standard-formed packets with the IP
      Diffserv field set to 0", or, more succinctly, "IP-type-P-connectivity
      with the IP Diffserv Field set to 0", since standard-formed is already
      implied by convention. Changing the contents of a field, such as the
      Diffserv Code Point, ECN bits, or Flow Label may have a profound affect
      on packet handling during transit, but does not affect a packet's status
      as standard-formed.</t>

      <t>A particular type of standard-formed packet often useful to consider
      is the "minimal IP packet from A to B" - this is an IP packet with the
      following properties:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="+">It is standard-formed.</t>

          <t hangText="+">Its data payload is 0 octets.</t>

          <t hangText="+">It contains no options or extension headers.</t>
        </list>(Note that we do not define its protocol field, as different
      values may lead to different treatment by the network.)</t>

      <t>When defining IP metrics we keep in mind that no packet smaller or
      simpler than this can be transmitted over a correctly operating IP
      network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conclusions">
      <t>This memo adds the key considerations for utilizing IPv6 in two
      critical conventions of the IPPM Framework. It is RECOMMENDED to adopt
      these new considerations in measurements involving IPv6.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations that apply to any active measurement of
      live paths are relevant here as well. See <xref target="RFC4656"/> and
      <xref target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

      <t>When considering privacy of those involved in measurement or those
      whose traffic is measured, the sensitive information available to
      potential observers is greatly reduced when using active techniques
      which are within this scope of work. Passive observations of user
      traffic for measurement purposes raise many privacy issues. We refer the
      reader to the privacy considerations described in the Large Scale
      Measurement of Broadband Performance (LMAP) Framework <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-lmap-framework"/>, which covers active and passive
      techniques.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo makes no requests of IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors thank Brian Carpenter for identifying the lack of IPv6
      coverage in IPPM's Framework, and for listing additional distinguishing
      factors for packets of Type-P. Both Brian and Fred Baker discussed many
      of the interesting aspects of IPv6 with the co-authors, leading to a
      more solid first draft: thank you both.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2330'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2675'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2679'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2780'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3168'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3432'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4494'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4656'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5357'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5644'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5835'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6049'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6282'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6437'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6576'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6703'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7045'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7312'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6808'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6985'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3148'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-lmap-framework'?>

      <reference anchor="Mat98">
        <front>
          <title>Empirical Bulk Transfer Capacity</title>

          <author fullname="Matt Mathis" initials="M." surname="Mathis">
            <!-- fullname="M.Mathis" -->

            <organization>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="December" year="1998"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IP Performance Metrics Working Group report in Proceeding of the Forty Third Internet Engineering Task Force, Orlando, FL."
                    value="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/98dec/slides/ippm-mathis-98dec.pdf"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
